

João Pereira

ENGINEER · DEVELOPER

Rua D. Afonso 71, Apt. 102 Ed. ACF - Arcozelo · 4750-222 Barcelos · Barcelos, Braga, Portugal

■ pereiraffjoao1993@gmail.com | ♣ joaofpereira.github.io | ☑ joaofpereira | ☐ jpereira93 | ✔ jfpereira93

Summary.

Currently, I'm working at Semasio/Fyllo as a Senior Backend Developer. My main focus is on implementing and enhancing performance on .NET micro-services that compose the company's product.

During my period on Semasio I have also enhanced my knowledge on system architecture, distributed systems, low-level programming and DevOps.

I'm a former student of Informatics and Computing Engineering on FEUP (Faculdade Engenharia da Universidade do Porto), where I was invited to be Teacher Assistant during two consecutive years on the Computer Graphics course. During my thesis, I made some research work to LIACC (Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory) on FEUP.

Good to mention that my main technological stack is, at the moment, C#.

As off-work interests, I spent a lot of time watching sports, cooking, travel, and studying new technologies.

Education

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto (FEUP)

Porto, Portugal

MSc. in Informatics and Computing Engineering

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2017

GPA: 16 out of 20

Escola Secundária de Barcelinhos

Barcelos, Portugal

SCIENCES AND TECHNOLOGIES

Sep. 2008 - Jul. 2011

• GPA: 17 out of 20

Experience

Semasio/Fyllo Porto, Portugal

SENIOR BACKEND DEVELOPER May 2022 - Present

Cenas

Porto, Portugal

BACKEND DEVELOPER

Oct. 2019 - May 2022

• Cenas

Porto, Portugal

JUNIOR BACKEND DEVELOPER

Oct. 2017 - Oct. 2019

• Cenas

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto

Porto, Portugal

TEACHER ASSISTANT

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2017

- Teacher Assistant of Graphical Applications Laboratory, a 3rd year course of the programme Master's in Informatics and Computing Engineering.
- In this semester the programme focused on Phong illumination models, polygonal surface rendering, texture mapping, functionality and usability of event handling and user interaction and inter-process communications and mechanisms synchronisation.
- The programming languages explored were JavaScript, C/C++ and WebGL.

Porto, Portugal

1

TEACHER ASSISTANT
Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

- Teacher Assistant of Computer Graphics, a 2nd year course of the programme Master's in Informatics and Computing Engineering.
 In this semester the programme focused on 3D image synthesis (local and global lighting and visibility calculation), modelling (3D
- In this semester the programme focused on 3D image synthesis (local and global lighting and visibility calculation), modelling (3D meshes, curves, surfaces and solids), geometric transformations (2D/3D), interaction and concepts for the development of graphical interfaces.
- The programming languages explored were JavaScript, C/C++ and WebGL.

Extracurricular Activity

ACADEMIC

JuniFEUP (Junior-company of FEUP)

• Gained expertise in the web development field.

Porto, Portugal

Mar 2015 - Jul 2016 TRAINEE

Skills_____

Programming $C# \equiv \cdot C/C + + \equiv \cdot Python \equiv \cdot Java \equiv \cdot Java Script \equiv$

Frameworks .NET =

Databases MySQL **=** ⋅ MongoDB **=**

Practices High Performance Computing **≡** • Distributed Computing **≡** • System Architectures **≡** •

Others Microsoft Azure **=** • Git **=** • Data Science (scikit-learn, pandas) **=** • LaTeX **=**

Languages Portuguese (Mother-tongue) **=** • English **=**

Publications

CONFERENCE ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

2017 Transportation in Social Media: An Automatic Classifier for Travel-Related Tweets,

Porto, Portugal

João Pereira, Arian Pasquali, Pedro Saleiro and Rosaldo Rossetti 18th Portuguese Conference on Artificial Intelligence (EPIA)

DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-65340-2 30

2017 Characterizing Geo-located Tweets in Brazilian Megacities, João Pereira, Arian

Wixu, China

Pasquali, Pedro Saleiro, Rosaldo Rossetti and Nélio Cacho

The 3rd IEEE Annual International Smart Cities Conference (ISC2 2017) {In Press.}

DISSERTATIONS

2017 Social Media Text Processing and Semantic Analysis for Smart Cities, Supervised by Rosaldo Rossetti and Pedro Saleiro | Grade of 19 out of 20.

Porto, Portugal

Master's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { arxiv: 1709.03406v1 }

Projects

Cafeteria Franchising Terminal

Mobile Computing Course

Android - Java · Express - Node.js · PostgreSQL

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2017

- This project consists in the development of two independent applications for Android devices.
- · The client-side applications allows clients to buy anything they want and after that a QR code is generated to be presented in the Cafeteria terminal application which is responsible to make all the payment process through the client credit-card number.
- An API was implemented to make easier the control of all transactions and operations. Both client-side and terminal application can communicate with it. When the server is offline, the application are implemented to communicate with it when the connection establishes again.

Currency Converter Mobile Computing Course

C# - XAMARIM · SQLITE

JQUERY · JAVA · ANTLR

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2017

- This project consists in the development native application for Android and Windows devices using the cross-platform Xamarim.
- The goal of the application is to support users regarding the conversion of different currencies (e.g. euros to dollars).
- · The application updates, when possible, the current value of every currency when it starts through the Yahoo Finance API.

JiQuery Compilers Course

• A tool implemented to translate valid jQuery selectors into executable Java code.

Feb. 2015 - Jul. 2015

· ANTLR was used to help in the development of lexical, syntactic and semantic representation functions to translate the code.

Mastermind

Formal Methods in Soft. Eng. Course

VDM++ · Java Sep. 2015 - Feb. 2016

· Mastermind, a board game, was implemented using Vienna Development Method (VDM++) to validate all the operations and objects that will constitute the source-code in a Java version.

Dashboard360Information Systems Course

C# - .NET · HTML5 · CSS3 · MICROSOFT SQL SERVER

Sep. 2015 - Feb. 2016

• Dashboard360 is a tool that allows companies to see the overall statistics of its businesses. This tool needs to be connected to an ERP Primavera to get all the necessary information to build the visual representations.

PollHub Web Lang. and Technologies Course

PHP · HTML5 · CSS3 · SQLITE

Sep. 2015 - Feb. 2016

• PollHub is a website where people can create polls quickly and invite others to participate.

skFEUP Database & Web Apps. Lab. Course

PHP - SMARTY · HTML5 · CSS3 · POSTGRESQL

Feb. 2015 - Jul. 2015

• AskFEUP is a Q&A platform built using the template engine Smarty. Users can create, answer, comment and classify questions as well as its respective answers.

Eximo Graphical Applications Lab. Course

C++ · PROLOG · OPENGL

Sep. 2014 - Feb. 2015

• Eximo is a board game with a 3D visualiser client developed in C++/OpenGL and the whole game logic is in charge of a Prolog server.

Honors & Awards

DOMESTIC

2016 4th Place, Hack a City, hackacity.eu/porto

Porto, Portugal